<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before my lord major at Guild-Hall Chappel on the 30th of Octob., 1681 by George Hooper ...</title>
            <author>Hooper, George, 1640-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13469921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13469921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 790:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before my lord major at Guild-Hall Chappel on the 30th of Octob., 1681 by George Hooper ...</title>
                  <author>Hooper, George, 1640-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mark Pardoe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: first page (half-title?) lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Galatians V, 22-23 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:99674:1"/>
            <head>Moore Major.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Cura Specialitent. Die Dominico, XXX. Octob.</hi> 1681. <hi>Anno. R. R. Caroli Secundi Ang.</hi> &amp;c, <hi>XXXIII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Court doth deſire Dr. <hi>Hooper</hi> to print his Sermon, preached this morning at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel before the Lord Major and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaff.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99674:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before my Lord Major, AT GUILD-HALL CHAPPEL, ON The 30th, of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>By GEORGE HOOPER, D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Mark Pardoe</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black Raven</hi> over againſt <hi>Bedford</hi> Houſe in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99674:2"/>
            <head>To the Right HONOURABLE Sir JOHN MOORE, Knight, Lord Major OF THE City of <hi>London</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe, as it doth juſtifie its becoming now more Publick, by ſo good an Authority, as that which it hath Prefixed: ſo is too to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that it owes that Honour to the Subject, of which it treats. Thoſe Graces of the Bleſſed ſpirit were likely to procure favour, from your Lordſhip, to One that did but mention their Names: and might be
<pb facs="tcp:99674:3"/>underſtood well enough, tho in an Imperfect Deſcription, by Such as were no Strangers to them. That the Holy Ghoſt may proceed to exhibit them to your Lordſhip, and your Brethren, in their own Life, and full Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; that by the Influence of your Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Love, and Joy, and Peace may be once again Reſtor'd amongſt us; that by ſuch Fruit your City may flouriſh Now, and your ſelves be everlastingly happy here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt Obedient Servant,
<hi>George Hooper.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99674:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>5 GALAT. 22, 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But the Fruit of the Spirit, is Love, Joy, Peace, Longſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Will not leave you comfortleſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">14 S. Joh. 18.</note> ſaid our Bleſſed Saviour upon his Departure to the disconſolate Diſciples: <hi>I will come unto you.</hi> And this promiſe he afterwards graciouſly verified, in the Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt: when the Divine Nature came yet nearer to them, then it had before done in the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; did not take fleſh apart, and conſtitute a diſtinct man; but United it ſelf in particular to each Believer, came in unto them, and dwelt within them: not now to work its wonders in its own Perſon or only to declare Laws; but to endue others with that Power of Miracles, and to enable us all for the mighty works of Obedience, to perform thoſe his commands.</p>
            <p>That is the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the Spirit, ſpoke in the ſame Chapter, <hi>and given to every one to profit withal.</hi> But, becauſe too there are Differences of Spirits; and thoſe as great, as between the Holy and the Wicked, the Bleſſed and the Accurſ'd; becauſe it is neceſſary to know which to ask of God, and cheriſh in our ſelves,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99674:4"/>which we ſhould command to avoid, and get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us; <hi>And the things of God knoweth no man but the ſpirit of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.11.</note> This manifeſtation is not yet clear, till we are taught to diſcern the Spirit; and till the Holy Ghoſt in farther favour to us, ſhall have inform'd us of the Manner and Signs of it's bleſſed Preſence: How it operates, and where it is to be preſum'd.</p>
            <p>And if the Operation of our Souls, the Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Underſtanding, and Inclination of the Will, afford ſuch Advantagious and delightful Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Rational minds; Our thoughts being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way better entertain'd, nor further improv'd, then by ſuch Reflections: The motions of the holy Spirit within us, the Actings of that new Divine Soul, as they are infinitely more exalted, and more Concerning; ſo are they a far Nobler, and much more neceſſary Subject for our moſt attentive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour entred upon this Subject, in Anſwer to <hi>Nicodemus.
<note place="margin">5. Joh. 3.8.</note> The wind,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>bloweth where it liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof,</hi> &amp;c. Not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us, to know the Holy Spirit by the ſound; for we may hear of it loudly, where it is not: Nor that we ſhould expect it always in Storms and Tempeſts; but to inform us that it's Suſtance is Inviſible, and that it is diſcernable only by the Effects. And after thoſe Effects we are now to inquire.</p>
            <p>That therefore we may know how to ſtir up the gift of God that is in us; and may duely thank him, for thoſe Graces of his, we find in our ſelves, or in our Brethren; that we may not be deluded, by our own Imaginations, or others Pretences; let me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you a little while into ſo noble, ſo uſeful a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99674:4"/>while the Spirit, in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> tells you what Fruit of it ye are to expect in your ſelves, and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fruit of the Spirit,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>is Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Temperance.</hi> And in theſe words you may conſider, 1. The Natures, of theſe Graces; and their orderly Production, 2. Their Beauty, and Advantage, and, 3. Our obligation to Produce them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The <hi>Love,</hi> here firſt mentioned, is the ſame with that you find throughout the whole New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſometimes under it's own Name, ſometimes under that of Charity: and is nothing elſe but the Love, with which the Chriſtian is affected to God, firſt, and then for God's ſake to his Brethren. This Fruit contains the Seeds, of thoſe that follow: the Holy Spirit producing the reſt from it, in a moſt Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral manner. And this, how it is raiſed it ſelf; we are firſt to Conſider.</p>
            <p>And, in order to this, it will be neceſſary to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that one of thoſe Graces, which reſults from Love, and is here rendred Faith, ought not to be taken for that Faith by which we become Chriſtians, but for Faithfulneſs or Fidelity: as will appear hereafter. The initiating Faith, whereby we aſſent to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, being here preſuppos'd; and leading us to Love: as Love will afterwards incline us to Fidelity.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtle begins here,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.13.</note> where he ended in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> There, after he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd the Temporary Inſtrumental uſe of thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous gifts, which Shin'd out in ſome Chriſtians for the Benefit of others, he directs them earneſtly to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99674:5"/>covet the Better; thoſe which were to abide, and were neceſſary to their own Salvation. <hi>And now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>abideth Faith, Hope, Charity, theſe three.</hi> And as theſe three have the preſerence before thoſe other afore mentioned; For they tended only to excite Faith, the firſt of theſe: ſo, amidſt theſe too, the Preeminence is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Laſt. <hi>But the greateſt of theſe is Charity.</hi> Faith and Hope themſelves, being but of a Tranſitory Nature in reſpect of Love: they ſerving, only to create that; and not Continuing in the next World. And this Love he there largely Commends, by the Effects; of which, he here gives us a more Particular enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For this Reaſon the Apoſtle mentions here neither Faith nor Hope, the Preparatory Graces: But begins with Love, their Perfect work, and this agreeably to the ordinary Method of the bleſſed Spirit, whoſe Gifts he now deſcribes. For ſo, in the Acts of the Apoſtles, after the New Convert had given Aſſent to the Doctrine of Chriſtianity, and in Hope of it's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes had been Baptiz'd; then it was, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles laid on their hands, and the Holy Ghoſt deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The Spirit had indeed before ſecretly Co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to that Faith, and Encourag'd that Hope; It had privately Prepar'd for it ſelf a fitting Manſion; but did not make it's publick Entry, till the Temple was ready: When thoſe previous Graces were form'd before, then it ſolemnly appeared; and thorough them powerfully exerted it ſelf; either in Signs and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or in the more deſireable Fruits, thoſe here of the Text.</p>
            <p>When therefore the Holy Ghoſt was come it did in many believers of the firſt Age, for the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99674:5"/>of thoſe that believed not, ſo exalt the Faith it found, and endue it with ſuch an Extraordinary force; that the Chriſtians, in the ſtrength of their pure Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, wrought the greateſt Miracles: and were able, by no more of it than might be compar'd to a grain of Muſtard ſeed, to remove Mountains: to ſuch Effects the Bleſſed Spirit advanced the Nature of Faith, in a ſingular manner, on a Particular occaſion. But it was however always to be underſtood that then the Operation was moſt Divine, and the improvement moſt Natural; when from Faith and Hope, God giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the increaſe, there aroſe Love, their Proper ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Fruit: whoſe Production you are now to ſee.</p>
            <p>For when a man by a ſtedfaſt lively Faith ſhall be aſſur'd of the Exiſtence of his God, as firmly as he is of his own; and ſhall have on his Mind any ſuitable Conception of the Divine Nature, any view of thoſe ineffable Tranſcendent Perfections; ſhall have once diſcover'd the Eternal, Immortal, Omnipotent, All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the abſolutely Holy, Juſt, and moſt infinitely Good: As he cannot but fall down Proſtrate before all this Greatneſs, and adore the Majeſty; ſo muſt he, if there be in him any reſemblance of ſuch qualities, be infinitely affected at the ſight of ſo much Purity, and paſſionately devote himſelf to ſo great Goodneſs. Had man no Intereſt in thoſe Attributes, did he ſtand by only, and ſee, and were the Kindneſs of the Goſpel directed to the Angels; yet certainly he could not but take part, and concern himſelf to Eſteem and to Love; he would be naturally attracted, and fix'd on ſuch an Object, by the tendency of a Rational Soul, the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy (if I may ſo ſay) of a Spiritual Being. But if he ſhall find himſelf the happy Object of all that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99674:6"/>Goodneſs, that all thoſe Glorious Attributes ſhine on him; if by the ſame Faith he ſhall come to learn that this Being, of ſuch inconceivable Perfection, was wonderful in nothing more, then in his love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and had prevented any Affection we could ſhew, by one conceived for us before the foundation of the World: when he ſhall reflect by what hand he is made, and whoſe likeneſs he has the honour to bear; that himſelf, whatſoever he values himſelf upon, or whatever he delights in, is owing all to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity of the ſame Cauſe: when he ſhall have read in the holy writings ſuch paſſionate expreſſions of good will, how earneſtly and concernedly the Almighty beſpeaks us, how willing he is to pardon, &amp; how glad to reward; how he lovesus more, then we do our ſelves; in one inſtance, appear'd to love us more, then he loved his ſo only Begotten Son: when man ſhall have perceived much love for him, from a Being ſo infinitely to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd himſelf: if he retains any thing of the Image of his Maker: will he not reſemble him in a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Affection? except he be yet but Earth, if he has any apprehenſion, any ſenſe, will he not diſcover it by grateful dutiful reſentment? he might as well, at the Creation, have refuſs'd to Live; as now, to Love.</p>
            <p>This way would a lively attentive Faith move. After it has laid before us the Hiſtory of the Divine Love, it would of it ſelf excite us to demonſtrations of our own.</p>
            <p>But further, when Faith hath given us ſuch a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous glorious <hi>Idea</hi> of the nature of God, ſuch an Obliging Engaging repreſentation of his Goodneſs to man; and has had its proper effect upon us, has created in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99674:6"/>us a Due Value and Adoration for his Bleſſed being, an approbation of his holy Will, and a warm zealous Devotion to his ſervice: It then too begins to give us the confidence of entitling our ſelves more peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Favour of God, and we preſume of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt in his gracious Promiſes; Aſſur'd of the Veracity of his Love, and conſcious of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our own, we look not only on the paſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his goodneſs, but expect the Glories of the future; and hope now as earneſtly for Heaven, as we certainly believe it.</p>
            <p>And, if Faith alone, which is in it ſelf but a paſſive Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on the Mind, has that force in it as to be the cauſe of ſo much Love; This Hope when once conceived, being of a Moving Active Nature, will not fail to quicken our deſires anew; and abſolutely inflame our Divine Affection. To ſum up then the whole, The ſoul, having from Faith the glorious amiable view of God's Infinite Perfections; together with the Hiſtory of his Exceeding Kindneſs, his undeſerved and unchangeable Affection to Mankind; and ſeeing too before its eye, by Hope, the proſpect of Heaven, its aſſur'd, bleſſed, immortal expectations; which way will it turn it ſelf, where it ſhall not ſee cauſe to, Love and to admire? It muſt give it ſelf up, encompaſſed on all ſides, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with infinite Attractives, and everlaſting Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. If any Perſon is to be beloved; it is this, which Faith preſents; if any paſt Favours can engage us; none earlier, nor greater, then His: If any Future Hopes can prevail; none more Certain, nor more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then thoſe. And theſe Bands of Love, each of them ſingly would certainly hold, and fix us Irremova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: but joyn'd together, and Twiſted in a threefold
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99674:7"/>Cord, they are impoſſible to be broken.</p>
            <p>And ſo far have I repreſented to you theſe workings of Faith and Hope, after the manner of Nature, and without the Co-operation of the Holy Spirit. But if we ſhall ſuppoſe, that God himſelf comes in, enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens our Underſtanding, and warms our Affections; if he ſhall be pleas'd to draw the lovely Image of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on our Minds, to form in us a right Senſe of all his Goodneſs, and a true Conception of his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Joys, to enliven the Thoughts, and actuate the Motions of the Soul; What raptures and extaſies are we then to ſuppoſe? Whom then would we have but God? And whom ſhould we deſire on Earth in Compariſon of him? Then ſhould we be all on fire from Heaven; <hi>And a Flame kindled in us, that many Waters would not quench, neither could the Floods drown:</hi> Our Love for him would reſemble his Divine Nature; and as much ſurpaſs any Worldly Paſſion, as God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells the Creation.</p>
            <p>This then is the Holy Paſſion of thoſe, that are grown up, in Chriſt, to their full Stature. This is the Fire they are Baptiz'd with, who are Baptiz'd with the Holy Ghoſt. And, as ſoon as the Breathings of the Spirit have blown up and kindled it, Man has, as it were, a New Soul, and becomes a New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; diſcerns his Heavenly Parent, and begins to Cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father. His greateſt Speculative pleaſure is in the Contemplation of this infinite excellent Wiſdom, Holineſs, and Goodneſs; and his greateſt Practical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the mean humble Performances, of that little Service he can be thought to do, of all that Honour he ſhall be allowed to Pay. Our Love then to God is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that of God for man: we Worſhipping and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99674:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erving by the ſame Principle, that he created and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, out of free Choice and pure Inclination; indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring now to pleaſe him by the ſame Motive, he has Prepar'd for us thoſe Eternal Pleaſures, by the Motive of a real Affection. We ſhould be ſo much New-men; that we ſhould not love our ſelves, but as we are the Workmanſhip, and the Care of a God: no other reaſon ſhould diſpoſe us to affect our ſelves, then what carries us to affect the reſt of mankind, all made, all in ſome meaſure beloved, by our Great Creator.</p>
            <p>And this is the Love here firſt plac'd; ſo much mention'd by our Saviour, and his Apoſtles; ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently viſible in their Heavenly lives, and willing Deaths. It is this Love towards God for his own ſake, and for him towards our Brethren, that performs all the commands, makes the full character of a Chriſtian; and is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred juſtly before, all other Graces; the Perfection of ſuch as go before and the Parent of thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. A love for Mankind unconceivable brought our Saviour down from Heaven, ſubjected a God to the meanneſs and infirmity of our mortal Nature, to the Agonies of the Garden, and the Death of the Croſs; induc'd him to lay aſide his Glorious Happineſs above, that he might <hi>bear our Griefs, and carry our Sorrows, might be wounded for our Tranſgreſſions, and bruis'd for our Iniquities.</hi> And a Love reſembling that infinitely deſerv'd by it, and Kindled at it, a Love of Gratitude and Duty burning in his Diſciples, in a juſt return and humble Emulation, devoted back their Bodies and their Souls to the Honour of him that had redeem'd them; Conſecrated, and Sacrificed their Lives, to the Service of that bleſſed Name: Out of affection to their Saviour, and to thoſe whom their Saviour Lov'd, they publiſh'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99674:8"/>the Propitiation of his Death, with the Peril of their own: They too in their Office of Reconciliation. <hi>Deſpis'd the Shame, and endured the Torment; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in their Sufferings, and filling up that which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind of the Afflictions of Chriſt.</hi> On ſuch Love of our Saviours is our Salvation founded: by ſuch Love of the Apoſtles is the good Tidings declar'd: and with the ſame in us is the Goſpel to be entertain'd and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd.</p>
            <p>Now, tho in an Age ſo luke-warm as Ours, theſe Holy Fervours of the Heavenly Love may not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly underſtood; tho to ſome this Gift of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may be as ſtrange, as that of Miracles, and may ſeem to have ceas'd as well; yet what Chriſtian is there that will not Profeſs he knows God? And who can know him that does not Love him? This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Fruit of the Spirit, in thoſe in whom he dwells: and from this Fruit the other that follow, do as naturally ariſe.</p>
            <p>As, 2. <hi>Joy,</hi> and this is the inſeparable Companion of Love, It's neareſt Attendant. Delight, Complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Satisfaction, ſurrounding it on every ſide, we being pleaſed with the Object, before we Love; Pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it while we Love; and pleas'd with the Love it ſelf, for ſo muſt our Joy have begun early, grown up, and heightned, from the ſame Diſcoveries of Faith, and by the ſame Proportions, by which our Love ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Believing,</hi> we ſhall not only Love with a Love not to be expreſſed, but <hi>Rejoyce</hi> too <hi>with Joy unſpeakable.</hi> For, as the Creation is cheer'd at the Riſing of the Sun; as Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal thinking Minds are raviſh'd, at the Diſcovery of ſome noble Truth; ſuch muſt the Joy be, but of an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99674:8"/>higher degree; when the Day dawns, and the Day-ſtar ariſes in our Hearts, and God himſelf ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he ſhall ſhine in upon us with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Glory, and reveal the Excellencies of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; when Greatneſs ſhall be diſcover'd in all it's Majeſty, Honour in all it's Luſtre; when Holineſs, Juſtice, Truth, and Goodneſs, ſhall be ſeen in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt <hi>Idea,</hi> and utmoſt Perfection. This ſight, as it will be hereafter, Clear, and at Hand, is juſtly ſtil'd the Beatifical Viſion; and may, of it ſelf, make Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs enough for a Heaven: And here on Earth as much of it, as the Eye of Faith may let in, would create on the Soul of man a Pleaſure, it had never before known, not to be experimented by Sence, or fanci'd by Imagination; a joy that we could not well bear; and which is to come mix'd and allay'd, in Mercy to our mortal Conſtitution. <hi>Many there are that ſay;
<note place="margin">Pſ. 4.6.</note> who will ſhew us any Good? But the Lord lifts up the light of his Countenance, on thoſe</hi> he Loves; <hi>And puts Gladneſs in their Heart,</hi> more then <hi>what Corn and Wine and Oyl</hi> would give. So much Pleaſure have we from Faith,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.15.</note> in the bare Speculation of God: we <hi>behold his Face</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and are <hi>Satisfi'd.</hi> God ſaw the Creation, delighted in it, and pronounc'd it good: what judgment then muſt they make? And what Joy will they find? That look on him.</p>
            <p>But then too if we proceed to the other Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Faith, as it relates to our ſelves; Whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver delight God might take in creating of Man; man cannot have more, then to find himſelf the Work of God; that we have the Honour to come out of his Hands, and the Happineſs to be Conſider'd by him. On what other occaſion ſhould we expreſs a greater
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99674:9"/>Joy. Then when we know our ſelves to be under the Care of his Providence, and guard of his Protection not be his Creatures only; but Friends in his Houſe, and Sons of his Family. And if this Joy be interrupted, by the Senſe of our Guilt, and dread of his Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet it is only ſtopt a while, to break out in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abundance, when that fear ſhall be remov'd, and the glad Tidings of a Pardon come: When, after a Cloud, and Showers, the light ſhall return Clearer, and his Love ſhall ſhine again upon us, with a more ſervent heat. At the Converſion of a Sinner, Angels rejoyce above: and ſhall not the Sinner rejoyce below, at his own Salvation? So, we ſee, as Faith goes on, it multiplies our Joy: which Hope raiſes yet higher; when it ſhows us Heaven before us, cheers us with that happy Proſpect, and bleſſes us with our Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Expectations. And this way does Joy riſe equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Love, and proceed diſtinctly from the ſame cauſes. It will too, that our Joy may abound, take yet a new Root, and ſpring out of Love it ſelf. For perfect Love, and aſſur'd of a reciprocal affection, as that is which the Spirit inſpires, <hi>caſteth out Fear, and has no Torment;</hi> Is full of Cheerfulneſs, and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: is, in it's own Nature, the ſweeteſt, the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, and moſt agreeable Motion of the Mind. And laſtly, as we obſerv'd of Love, that it's Motives from Faith and Hope were powerful enough in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but invincibly Prevalent, when inforc'd by the bleſſed Spirit: ſo is the Joy, that ariſes from them and Love, certain and ſure in it's immediate Cauſes, and neceſſary from their Natural influence; but exalted yet more by the Concurrence of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſuper naturally enlarg'd by it's Operations. For the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99674:9"/>Motions of the Holy Spirit within us cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be, but in the moſt grateful Cheerful manner: It is the Spirit of Comfort, and Conſolation; and in it's Preſence are fulneſs of Joys: as the Property of the Wicked one is to torment; to infuſe Grief, and Anguiſh, Sadneſs, and Deſpair.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From Love and Joy ſprings <hi>Peace,</hi> of both kinds: of the Mind, and Conſcience within; and to the World, abroad. In ſuch a breaſt is no diſorder, nor trouble: nothing but content, and ſatisfaction; a Quiet and Serenity as if it were in Heaven: no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward accidents, nor inferior cares can diſcompoſe it. And if peace be preſerved within, it will appear in our converſation; and we ſhall be as eaſy to others as to our ſelves. In thoſe paſſions of Joy and Love the Spirits move outwards; and diffuſe the ſweetneſs and equality of their temper into all our Actions. Here will be no Envy, Anger, nor Diſcontent: we ſhall not be Turbulent, Diſorderly, nor ſeditious.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thence too Long-ſuffering: not eaſy to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd, diſturb'd, or provoked; by ſufferings, by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, by failing of better expectations. None of theſe things will move Minds, that are wholly ſet upon their God; nor will their divine Joy ſuffer them, to be ſenſible of the lighter momentary afflictions. So far will they be from being haſty, froward, captious, querulous, and repining.</p>
            <p n="5">5. From the ſame cauſe is <hi>Gentleneſs,</hi> or ſweetneſs of Temper; to be ready to forgive, and eaſy to be reconcil'd: this will be done, in imitation of Gods; Love to us; and out of Love to our Brethren, for God's ſake. Beſides that Joy of it ſelf diſpoſes to pardon opens our Heart, and our Arms.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99674:10"/>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Goodneſs</hi> too is perfect from the ſame principle: as we here may take it, for an Univerſal Kindneſs, Pitty, and Compaſſion; to be ready to do all good Offices to all the world, in the moſt obliging manner; out of Affection, and with Joy.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Faith, which here follows, is as I premiſed before, ſitly underſtood by Integrity, or Fidelity, and the reaſon of this rendering may recommend it the more to the better part of this Audience. Theſe two words Faith and Meekneſs, as they are joyned here, ſo are they found together in Elder Authors; and probably in the ſame ſignification.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.27.</note> As in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus: Faith and Meekneſs are Gods Delight;</hi> and afterwards in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Moſes, <hi>he ſanctified him with Faithfulneſs and Meekneſs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 45, 9 4.</note> (where faithfulneſs is, in the <hi>Greek,</hi> the ſame with the Faith before.) And theſe two Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, that make up here the Character of the greateſt Magiſtrate, and wiſeſt Governour Moſes; are the ſame that are recorded in the Book of Numbers. The firſt, this of Fidelity, God himſelf gives him: <hi>My ſervant Moſes who is Faithfull in all my houſe.</hi> The other of Meekneſs,
<note place="margin">Numb. 12.3.</note> the Holy Writer makes his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar commendation. <hi>Now this man Moſes was the meekeſt man in all the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 12 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Faithfulneſs of Moſes appear'd eminently, in the whole courſe of his Miniſtry, in the Delivery of his Meſſages, and diſcharge of his Duty; but moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably amidſt the Rebellious Prevarication of the People Iſrael. He never Connived at their Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, nor gave Countenance to their Ingratitude, His Brother had ſuffered himſelf to be led by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſet up a Molten Image: But Moſes is never found in their murmurings, and diſcontents; He kept
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99674:10"/>his integrity, and preſerv'd his Loyalty to his God. His Meekneſs too was as ſingular. Not Fierce, Proud, and Haughty, Arrogant, and Imperious; but Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, Humble, and Affable. This being that other part of the Character of that holy Governour, and the Signification of the Word here tranſlated Meek, and anſwering to the Hebrew Notion of Lowlineſs and Modeſty.</p>
            <p>For this reaſon we take leave to render the word Faith, by Faithfulneſs. When God gave <hi>Moſes</hi> of his Holy Spirit, this was the Fruit. And in this Senſe, it comes here moſt Properly amongſt the other atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of Divine Love. It being here, as in Conjugal affection; where Fidelity and Truth are the moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and moſt neceſſary Companions of that and Peace.</p>
            <p>For when our Affection is once engaged to God; there will follow a faithful Perſeverance in all known Duties; Obedience to laws Divine, and Humane; Loyalty to God, and his Repreſentatives. But on the contrary, when Love and Peace are baniſhed; and Hatred, Animoſity, Faction, and Sedition take place; they preſently introduce Prevarication, Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Treachery; they are the conſtant Cauſes of Calumny, Slander, Falſhood, and Perjury. As Satan the firſt Rebel, is the known Father of Lyes.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The other Grace of <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> as oppos'd to inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, is too a Fruit that neceſſarily grows from Love. For that diſpoſition of mind as it is Peaceable, Eaſie, and Gentle; So too does it equal, and Level; and reſpects all Mankind, but as Brethren of the ſame Houſe, tho under differing Circumſtances. This cauſes that the Superiors ſtoop, and Condeſcend; are not harſh, nor Supercilious; are Civil, Kind, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99674:11"/>Treatable. And if it has that Power over Governours, and makes the Character of a Magiſtrate; it may well become Subjects, and ſuit with thoſe of a lower de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. Humility, Modeſty, Deference, and Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are proper to their Station: as Inſolence, Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs, Affronting of Government, is both abſurd in Morals, and impoſſible in Charity, and neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts with the Spirit of God, nor with Order and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The laſt is <hi>Temperance:</hi> Which is but an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Love to God, in not preferring the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the World before him. For as the Spirit of God is Holy; and cannot dwell in a Body polluted: ſo neither can it be ſuppos'd; that a Soul accuſtom'd to Divine Love, and Spiritual Joys, ſhould reliſh any longer, thoſe ſenſual Satisfactions.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Fruit of the Spirit, with this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, and Dependance. Heavenly Love is the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of thoſe that follow; and they, like the iſſue of the ſame Parent, have indeed a near reſemblance; but ſo, that their Natures are diſtinct, and their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence diſcernable. Gifts fit for the Holy Spirit to give: and worthy each of a more particular deſcription.</p>
            <p n="2">II. And now after we have known and conſider'd them diſtinctly, I ſhall entreat you to beſtow one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon them all together. This Fruit how fair it is to the Eye, how Lovely, not forbid us as that of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; but given, and preſented: of which, if we have taſted; We are reſtored to a Condition of <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs greater then that deſign'd in</hi> Eden: <hi>We are become like Gods, and we ſhall live for ever:</hi> We have a Heaven in our Breaſts; we make the Sphere of our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99674:11"/>Converſation ſo to all about us. We are only leſs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py now, then we ſhall be hereafter; but in a Felicity begun already, of the ſame kind.</p>
            <p>For let us ſuppoſe, that God would appear bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to ſome Fortunate man here below. What Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhould we expect from Heaven? Power? or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? or Riches? they are not neceſſary Cauſes of a happy Life; are not inconſiſtent with Trouble, and Vexation: They are, what the World, Chance, or the Devil, may beſtow. But a gift, fit for a God to give, what can it be but himſelf? what can it be? But to bleſs our ſight with <hi>Moſes</hi> his view,
<note place="margin">Exod. 33.19.</note> a Diſplay of all his Excellencies; to <hi>Proclaim himſelf, and cauſe his Glory to paſs before us.</hi> To proclaim our ſtyle too, to call us his Friends, and adopt us for his Sons; to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh our Pardon aloud from Heaven, and declare his Love before all the Creation; to diſcover too to us, as to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> his future Glories, and to open his third Heaven to our view, and our Expectations; and Laſtly, till he ſhall take us up thither, to come down himſelf, to come unto us, and make his abode with us, to bring his Heaven here. In what trouble now ſhall that Breaſt be, that is ſecur'd of the affection of a God? and what other thing will he deſire, that Loves him? His preſent Fruition is greater then any thing, but his Hopes: And of thoſe too he is as well aſſured, as of what he now enjoys. His Peace no man can take from him: his Joy muſt be perfectly Compleat; and his Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on infinite.</p>
            <p>This inward Joy, when it fills and overflows the Heart, how will it Cheer and enliven the Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? What an agreeable Luſtre, and divine Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will it caſt? Then will the Face of man look
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99674:12"/>indeed like the Image of God; and diſcover by the Glory, who it is that dwells within. This Love burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inward, when it ſends forth its Light and its Heat, and ſhines out on others in Kindneſs, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, and Goodneſs, muſt too engage and warm their mutual Affections: Nothing can appear ſo Attrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, nothing ſo Lovely. The Temple of <hi>Salomon</hi> in all its Beauty, overlay'd with Gold within and without, and fill'd with the Glory of the Lord, was not ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as one of theſe Houſes under the ſecond Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as one of theſe Temples of the Holy Ghoſt. You have the Pourtraiture of this, in the Deſcription of St. <hi>Stephen. He was full of the Holy Ghoſt, and all that ſat in the Council looking ſtedfaſtly upon him,
<note place="margin">Act. 6.15.</note> ſaw his Face as it had been the Face of an Angel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Graces, if Vouch-ſafe'd to any Family, would recommend it in the Eyes of a diſcerning Heathen, to be more happy, then Plenty, Authority, or Greatneſs of Blood could make them. The Gentleneſs, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Meekneſs of the Maſter; the Fidelity, and Affectionate concern of the Inferior relations; Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance in all their Lives, and Joy in all their Faces; the Peace of man, and of God; the Correſpondence betwixt themſelves; and the Intercourſe of Love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, and Heaven: all this muſt make the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring Spectator take up <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſaying;
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.17.</note> 
               <hi>Surely the Lord is in this Place: this is no other, but the Houſe of God; and this the Gate of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were there but a City compos'd of ſuch Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; this yet would be but one Family, and like that now deſcribed: the Spirit of God dwelling in it, and his holy Protection watching over it: Peace within its Walls; and Plenteouſneſs within its Palaces: All
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99674:12"/>the Inhabitants nearer in their Perſons, then their Dwellings: the City eſteem'd, not from the beauty, proportion, or order of the Buildings, but from the ſymmetry, the Harmony of the Inhabitants. Such an Union as this is to make the true Neighbourhood, and the Happieſt Commerce. So compacted, it would have a ſurer ſtrength, then from Walls and Bulwarks. This would make it the Faireſt, the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the beſt order'd, the Richeſt City of the World. It would be like the Great City, the Holy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> deſcending from God, out of Heaven; at each Gate an Angel; its building of precious ſtones.</p>
            <p>For all Policies and Ordinances of the beſt conſtituted Cities: are but faint imitations of the Graces of the Spirit; are ſet up to procure the Shadow of Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, &amp;c. Joyning of Houſes deſigns uniting of Minds: a Corporation ſpeaks it ſelf to be one body: Companies and fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are appointed for nearer aſſociations; to make yet a firmer tye, then what reſults only from common intereſt. There are ſeaſons of Cheerfulneſs, and days of Joy: Civility thence call'd; and there learnt: affected Gentleneſs, and cuſtomary complaiſance, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Goodneſs, and Pretended Love. There is the profeſſion of faithful dealing; Order and Obedience are own'd; and Intemperance, as well as other Filth remov'd out of ſight; and from the obſervation of theſe rules, and the benefit of Peace and ſecurity, ariſes Wealth and Plenty. As on the contrary, when the manners of men are diſtant from any likeneſs of theſe Graces; when Hatred, Diſcontent, Variance, Spite, Inſolence even in ſubjects, Faithleſsneſs, Fraud, and Luxury come together and take place; a City
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99674:13"/>then is only an Aſſociation of Evils: and the Nuiſance as great, as the advantage that was intended. As Neighbouring houſes, at other times a common ſtrength are found too nigh in a Fire: and Company, the Comfort and convenience of mankind, is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in time of Infection; and it is their Wiſdom then to live at diſtance. If intemperance prevails in the Town; It is no better then a common receptacle of Impurity: if Fraud, and Perjury; it is but as a Den of Thieves: If Malice, Revenge, and Mutiny; it is as a place of Battle. <hi>If ye bite, and devour one another; take heed</hi> ſays the Apoſtle in this Chapter to the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, that ye be not Conſumed one of another.</hi> Neither is it needful to ſhew how Dammageable theſe Vices are to Commerce: and how impoſſible it is to manage it, in that Company. We may only obſerve that Tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs and Sedition are as great Enemies to Trade, as they are to Government; while they are growing they diſturb and hinder it; as hereafter, when they are form'd into a War they will plunder its Effects. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Animoſities take off mens Minds from the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of their Imployment; and Faction grows up to be a Trade: Men are Apprentices to other Myſteries; and ſet up for Politicians: and then no wonder, if our Commerce flouriſhes not; if Honeſty, and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Induſtry, Riches, and Plenty, go ſeek out other Dwellings. After a great and general Judgement of God, <hi>the Children of men went to make Bricks to build a City,
<note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> and a Tower that ſhould reach to Heaven.</hi> But, when by another juſt Judgement from the ſame righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hand they begun to vary, and ſpake not the ſame Language: they were ſcattered abroad, and left to the Place the name of Confuſion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99674:13"/>
            <p>So that, altho it is not fit to perſwade to theſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the advantages of Commerce; for they are gifts of the Holy Spirit, and to deſire them on any Temporal account, and to make Merchandize of them, would be a Crime againſt the Holy Ghoſt; and truely Simony: yet however their proper Intrinſick worth may be ſenſibly underſtood, by their viſible Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; and their Beauty will appear, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of their oppoſite Vices. The certain Effects of the one, are Poverty, Ruin, and Deſolation: And the natural tendency of the other, to Riches, Honour and Proſperity. With theſe, the ſpiritual Graces will probably bleſs us: but they will too make us Happy, without them; for they are able alone to give us the beſt Joy and ſureſt Satisfaction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here: and they only can conſign to us Everlaſting Happineſs, hereafter.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We ſhall therefore, in the third Place, conſider the greater Obligations we have to beg of the holy Spirit to produce this Fruit in us.</p>
            <p>And, 1. As Chriſtians in general. For this is the Fruit, which if the Tree beareth not, it will hereafter be hew'd down, and caſt into the Fire. And indeed we take only a Name in Baptiſme; and begin thence to be called Chriſtians, only for diſtinction ſake on Earth; for in Heaven it will give none: except a real Change is made in the Perſon, ſaid to be regenerate; and the Holy Ghoſt enters into the Temple, ſo purified by Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For by Baptiſme we are cut off from the Old ſtock; and grafted into the Body of Chriſt: but ſo as to cloſe, and grow, and bear Fruit. By it we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed dead unto all former Sin: but dead too and Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we continue; except we are quickned by his free
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99674:14"/>Spirit, Man in Baptiſm, being like <hi>Adam</hi> new form'd, and as yet but Clay; expecting the breath of his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and this we have ſeen, was the Method of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, our Saviour received, and the Apoſtles gave when the new planted Diſciples were <hi>Watered;</hi> then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>gave the Increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We therefore, that have not been <hi>baptized with the Baptiſm of John only,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19.</note> but <hi>know there is a Holy Ghoſt;</hi> ought to know our ſelves for true Chriſtians; by the true diſtinctive Character, its proper Fruit: not by a ſearch into a Baptiſmal Regiſter, but by what we find in our ſelves of theſe Graces; by the <hi>Seal of the Spirit.</hi> Our Title to the Name is not good; but after this Confirmation. Neither are we at our grown Age, to take our ſelves for Believers, if we ſtood at the Creed, not only to declare our Aſſent; but in the poſture of thoſe Warlike Chriſtians, with Swords drawn in its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: the true judgement of our Faith is not only, whether it be Reſolute, and Obſtinate; for that may be from a willful Mind: but whether the belief of the Divine Exiſtence be ſo Lively; the Repreſentation of his Perfections ſo clear, and diſtinct; the Sence of his Love to us ſo great, and engaging, as to oblige our mutual Affection; to Poſſeſs us with a delight, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Joy can equal; a Quiet, and Satisfaction, not to be interrupted here below; to inflame us with a Love for all his Images, the whole Race of mankind; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engage our Minds from all earthly Pleaſures, and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Satisfactions admitting no Rival with our God. This is the Catholick Apoſtolick Faith; and, who ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves ſo, ſhall not periſh everlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>Such a Faith as this, ſo well Rooted and ſo Fruitful, if it does differ in ſome leſſer Speculative points, yet is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99674:14"/>not like to be miſ-informed long: Its Meekneſs diſpoſes it for Inſtruction;
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.15.</note> and its Fidelity is ready to Confeſs the miſtake: <hi>And if in any thing he is otherwiſe minded;</hi> yet <hi>God the giver of all good and perfect Gifts,</hi> and who has given to him thoſe other already, <hi>will reveal even this unto him.</hi> And however, if the Error ſhall be ſuffer'd to continue; it will produce no ill Effect, under the Governance of Peace, Long-ſuffering, and Gentleneſs: And this ſtain may be Purg'd at laſt, by the Fire of Love; as others are ſaid to be, by that of Martyrdom. If then we find thoſe Qualities beſtow'd upon us; happy are we for the preſent, and ſecure for the Future, they are Gifts in their own Value ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable; but they are too Earneſts of a greater, <hi>of our eternal Inheritance, the Redemption of the purchas'd Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the firſt of theſe Graces, the Love of God, is the moſt natural Effect, the moſt certain Argument of a Chriſtian Faith: So, that we love God intirely, and ſolidly, not in Fancy only and conceit, in a holy Dream, the beſt Proofs we can produce, are its genuine reſults, the Fruit here mentioned; Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Fidelity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if in this age of Diſtinctions, we would diſcriminate betwixt thoſe that are Chriſtians, and thoſe that are not; Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our has given us a Text:
<note place="margin">St. Joh. 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples if ye Love one another.</hi> In vain ſhall ye pretend the love of God, or of his Son,
<note place="margin">St Joh. 4.20.</note> if it be not ſeen on your Brethren. <hi>He that ſays he loves God, and hates his Brother, is a Lyar.</hi> Says the loving, and beloved Apoſtle. A Lyar as great, as he that ſhould ſay he loved his Brother; and yet was provoked on the next Occaſion, never would Pardon him the leaſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99674:15"/>fault, and refus'd him the ſmalleſt kindneſs: as great a Lyar, as he that ſhould pretend Meekneſs, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; and yet be guilty of Treaſon, and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>By that Mark the Chriſtians of old were known: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how they love one another! ſaid the Heathen admiring their Unanimity; ignorant of the Spirit by which they were lead, of the Graces which ſo inclin'd them: but if one of thoſe Heathen had been acquainted with their powerful principle of Love; and yet had afterwards found them Diſcontented, Mutinous, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull, Factious, Paſſionate; he might have cryed out, Behold how they hate one another! with greater Admiration.</p>
            <p>The Qualities of the Text are the proper diſpoſition of a Chriſtian Mind: They are the Life, and Soul of our Holy Religion; all its Precepts, all its Inſtitutions, tend only to produce and cheriſh this Fruit. For all the Revelations of the Scripture are nothing elſe, but Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of God's Love to us; to create in us, a Love for him: and all its commands have no other intention then that this our Love to God, ſhould be exemplifi'd, in Affection to our Brethren; and demonſtrated, by our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference for all worldly Pleaſures. This is the ſum, the ſpirit of the Chriſtian Religion: into this we are baptiz'd: for this the Holy Ghoſt deſcends: and this Love the Bleſſed Supper feeds; by the pledges of Chriſt's Love, the continual remembrance of his Death, to our great and endleſs comfort. And however men may refine in their pretences; and be ſingular in their Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and titles of purer Profeſſions; if their doctrine does not at laſt determine, and center here; it is Chriſtian Religion falſely ſo called: it is counterfeit,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99674:15"/>and has not to it the Witneſs of the Holy Ghoſt.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>The end of the Commandment is Charity, out of a pure Heart, and good Conſcience, and Faith unfeign'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> for <hi>in Jeſus Chriſt neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; but Faith, which worketh by Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So Contradictorily do they Act to our holy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who think they may be malicious, diſorderly, falſe, perjur'd in its defence, ſo little do they conſider the Nature of God; who conſecrate their wicked Paſſions, and offer the Service of their Hatred and Anger to his Name; who like the Pope give Abſolution to all Luſts; that Liſt themſelves in a pretended holy War. <hi>For the Works of the fleſh are manifeſt,</hi> ſays our Apoſtle, <hi>which are theſe; Adultery, Fornication, Laſciviouſneſs, Idolatry, Witchcraft, Hatred, Variance, Aemulations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, Envyings, Murders, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, and ſuch like, of the which I tell you before; as I have alſo told you in Times paſt, that they who do ſuch Things ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God. But</hi> as the Text continues, <hi>the Fruit of the Spirit is Love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By this Fruit are all Chriſtians to be Sav'd.</p>
            <p>But 2. Thoſe are oblig'd to abound in this Fruit, in a more particular manner; who make a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar claim to the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that pretend to the Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, happy are they, if they have attain'd them. They ſeem ſenſible of thoſe bleſſed Influences, every good Chriſtian is to expect, and to Cheriſh: And pretend to no more, then what is neceſſary to the Salvation of each Believer. Neither is he yet partaker, in any Meaſure, of the Heavenly gift, that ſhall Envy it to any, that are called by the Name of Chriſt: Such a thought ſuits neither with the Love of God, nor of his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99674:16"/>Brother. <hi>Would God, that all the Lords people were Prophets;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 11.29.</note> ſaid the meek <hi>Moſes:</hi> when thoſe that ſhar'd of the Spirit; were too to have their part in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Beſides that the Holy Ghoſt himſelf has inform'd us, in his firſt Speech after his Deſcent, how largely he intended his Bounty. <hi>The Promiſe,</hi> ſays he by the mouth of St. <hi>Peter, is made to you, and to your Children,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.39.</note> and to all that are afar off; even as many as the Lord our God ſhall Call.</hi> God fulfill his Gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: and make all theſe Partakers of the Gift, that own it.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, becauſe a good Opinion of one's ſelf may be taken for the Holy Ghoſt; and we may not impoſe only on others, but our ſelves; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there cannot be a more dangerous deluſion, then to miſtake the lying Spirit for the Spirit of Truth, and to be Poſſeſſed, inſtead of being Inſpir'd; we are therefore commanded to make <hi>Tryal of the Spirits, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When then the Holy Spirit its ſelf is content to be tryed; he will betray a great want of it, that is not meek enough to ſubmit to the Examination.</p>
            <p>And here too, the Proof is to be by the Product. <hi>By their Fruits too ſhall ye know the Spirits.</hi> And the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of Life, will not fail preſently to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelf; by ſenſible ſigns, by ſtrong vital indicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>But the Effects, we are to Expect, are not Miracles, Curing of the ſick, or Raiſing of the Dead; they were Illuſtrious ſigns of the Divine preſence; are not heard of after the firſt Ages, nor mentioned here. They are not Talents of Eloquence and Diſcourſe, Copiouſneſs of Language, or a fluent Volubility in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99674:16"/>this ſeems to be of the ſame kind with the Gift of Tongues, and to have been but of Temporary uſe; here we are ſure not expreſſed. They are no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then thoſe you find recounted in our Text; they are Love, Joy, Peace, &amp;c. Things not ſo glorious indeed in the Eyes of Carnal men; but the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, moſt natural Effects of the Holy Ghoſt; as viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Marks, and as Convincing Proofs of his Preſence, as the louder, and ſeemingly more mighty Works.</p>
            <p>He then that lays a more particular Claim to the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Holy Spirit, is to ſhew it, by a Love more exalted towards God, and more enlarg'd toward man: extended in all its Dimenſions, <hi>Height, Breadth, Length, and Depth;</hi> to God our Soveraign in chief, to his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, to all Magiſtrates, all Superiors, to Equals on all ſides, and Inferiors of all kinds. He is to do Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Charity; to be a wonder of Contentedneſs, Peaceableneſs, Gentleneſs, Lowlyneſs, and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; His mighty works will be in Temperance, Goodneſs, and Fidelity.</p>
            <p>The Fathers of the Hermites of <hi>Syria</hi> are ſaid to have try'd the Spirit of an Anchorite, of a new kind, in one of theſe Qualifications, in Meekneſs, if he ſhew'd Submiſſion, and Humility; they Preſum'd the ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Poſture guilty of no Affectation nor Deſign.</p>
            <p>We may make a more certain Judgment, from all theſe ſigns the Text affords us. Nor will it be a Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing to view the Converſation of men, and to diſcern; whether their behaviour be more quiet and Peaceable; whether they are Patient, freer from mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and Complaint; Eaſie, Gentle, and Tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; not Cenſorious, nor Backbiters, not Proud, nor diſobedient; not given to the World, and its deſires,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99674:17"/>to Ambition, Covetouſneſs, or Cernality. Happy is he, on whom the difference is found: againſt him <hi>there is no Law.</hi> He is to be Cheriſhed, and eſteem'd by all; to be Bleſſed, and imitated by all good men.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, when a man is readier to Hate then to Love; ſo far from affecting his Brother for God's ſake, that he endures not his next Image upon Earth, his immediate Repreſentative; ſo full of Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and Malice, that the abundance of the Heart breaks out at the Mouth; where one ſearches for Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Complaint, and is fond of Grievance and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, is weary of Peace, wiſhes and prepares for War; ſo little Long ſuffering, that he is under In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, as if he were under Perſecution; Inſolent, Provoking, deſpiſing Dominion; pardoning not the leaſt defects, tho in his Father and Prince; Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niating, Slandering, Libelling even Autority it ſelf; making and delighting in a Lye, ſuborning Falſhood, and Confounding truth, Heady, Refractory, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient. The Evidences againſt this man's Pretences are ſo great; that, did he work Miracles, they muſt find no Credit; they too muſt be aſcribed, not to the bleſſed Spirit, but to him that works in the Children of Diſobedience. To aſſign them to a Divine cauſe, would be a Slander againſt the Righteouſneſs of God: would be, to Blaſpheme againſt the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>If there are among ye ſtrifes and Envying and Seditions are ye not Carnal and walk as men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the name then of God, and of Religion; let men, in Pretences of ſo high a Nature, at leaſt diſſemble well: let there be ſome colour of Love; ſome diſguiſe of Gentleneſs, Humility, and Obedience; let men ſee ſomething of the complexion and ſhape of this Fruit,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99674:17"/>ſomething the Holy Ghoſt may own: and they may then have leave to think Charitably and to preſume from what they do ſee, of what they cannot, that the Spirit dwells there. But to believe the Spirit to be, where there appears nothing but the works of the Fleſh; is the ſame abſur'd Creed with that of Tranſubſtantiation: it is to ſubdue our Reaſon, and Sence; ſo far, as to take that for a Sheep, which has the ſhape and qualities of a Wolf; to think that a Dove, that you ſee hiſs, and bite, and ſting.</p>
            <p>This was the caſe of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> When its Biſhops firſt began to Change their Title into an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Quality, to challenge Holyneſs to their Perſons, as well as in their ſtyle; when they pretended the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and Claim'd to be infallible; and reſted ſo far on that Preſumption, as to juſtifie their Actions by the Pretence, and not to take Care to make their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences good by Actions anſwerable; the World, tho held in by all Arts of Policy, and force of Power, yet could not but diſcover and reject the Impoſture; rather, then believe the Spirit ſhould dwell in ſuch reſtleſs ambitious bloody men, they abjudged it from the See; and thought it more reaſonable the Pope might err, then that the Doctrines of Image-Worſhip, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, and Tranſubſtantiation, ſhould be True, that Decrees for Perjury, Rebellion, deſpoſing and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Princes, ſhould come from God.</p>
            <p>This certainly: What ever ſort of men Attribute to themſelves the Spirit of God, in them ſhould be ſeen nothing but what is agreeable to it; nothing whereby it ſhould be grieved within, or diſhonoured without. Pure they ſhould be within, as thoſe that Lodge a God: And Careful of their outward Actions,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99674:18"/>as of ſuch as may be imputed to the Holy Ghoſt. For, to uſe our Apoſtles argument, Profeſs ye, <hi>That ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16.</note> If any man defile the Temple of God; him will God deſtroy. For the Temple of God is Holy: which Temple ye are.</hi> It is Holy; not ſo, as to bring a Neceſſity of Holineſs on your Actions; but to affect you with an unpardonable Guilt, if ye unhallow and profane it.</p>
            <p>The pretence to the Spirit ſo is it to be Examin'd by man: And when falſe, is in their ſight a bold Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But can it impoſe upon the Holy Ghoſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Or will the unlike Counterfeit appear leſs impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent before him? The divine Nature had before an irreconcileable Averſion to Wrath, Anger, and Hatred. But what an indignity and Provocation muſt this be to find it ſelf entitled to it? That, inſtead of mans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chang'd by the Spirit, the Spirit of God ſhould have received new impreſſions from Man. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were ſtruck Dead, for telling a ſingle untruth, concerning the Value of an Eſtate: They <hi>lye</hi> boldly <hi>to the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> whoſe Faſhoods are concerning himſelf. And till Interpreters ſhall be agreed, what hainous Crime is that Sin againſt him; well may this bear the Name.</p>
            <p>And may not the ſtrangeneſs of our preſent Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per prompt us to ſuſpect that the bleſſed Spirit has not only deſerted us, but abandon'd us to the Wicked one? For, if our Luxury, Variance, Aemulations, Perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Diſcontent, conſiſted with our Intereſt; if there were no temporal Danger that they threatned; were theſe Diviſions, in a time of Confeſſed ſafety, and general Security, and we at leiſure and Liberty to Quarrel: We might then be content to ſay, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99674:18"/>thoſe things were not the Fruit of the Spirit, were the Works of the Fleſh, and the fulfilling the Luſts thereof. But, when common Danger alarms us continually within, and threatens terribly from abroad; when the intereſt of the Liberty of our Native Country calls upon us to unite and arm, againſt the growing ſtrength of a Violent forraigner, and a Tyrannical Religion, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented upon the Point of his Sword; when all Moral Conſiderations joyn in with the Suggeſtions of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and call for Love and Peace, or we are utterly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd, here and for ever: then not to hearken, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue this unnatural feud, is not from the Fleſh on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from a Carnal mind, for that would have at leaſt Carnal prudential Thoughts; but is, one would fear, from the Prevalence of the Evil Spirit. There muſt be ſomething more then Humane, that is the cauſe of all this Infatuation: enough to juſtifie the Liberty of the Speaker, if he ſhould take up that of the Prophet <hi>Micaiah. I ſaw the Lord ſitting on the Throne of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and all the Hoſt of Heaven by him,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 22.9.</note> on his right Hand, and on his left. And the Lord ſaid, who ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Ahab to go up and fall?</hi> Who ſhall perſwade a Country full of the bleſſings of God, but ungrateful and unworthy, to give up, what they have forfeited; and execute God's wrath upon themſelves? Who ſhall perſwade a Country of ſo much Strength, Riches, Laber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Peace, to fall Voluntarily under Diſhonour, Poverty, and a forrain Yoak? In the Text, <hi>there came forth a Spirit and ſtood before the Lord, and ſaid; I will perſwade him. And the Lord ſaid, wherewith? And he ſaid, I will go forth, and I will be a Lying Spirit in the Mouth of his Prophets.</hi> And what is it but a Lying Spirit? That ſhall accuſe the beſt reform'd Church,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99674:19"/>of Popery; the eaſieſt Government under the Sun, of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny: that ſhall talk now of Grievances, and Impoſitions; and ſhall ſpeak of want of Trade, in times of the moſt flouriſhing Commerce: that ſhall haunt Places of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick reſort, and fly about the Land in Libellous Prints, with falſe Tales and miſhapen Truths to enrage the Minds of men, againſt lawful Government their only common Security; to confound our juſt fears with Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous jealouſies, and diſtract us in the Face of an Enemy with falſe Alarms. And if, to this Spirit, God ſhall have added ſeven more as wicked as the other. If he has mingled a perverſe Spirit in the midſt of us; a Spirit deaf to the Voyce of the Charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely, hearkening to no Accommodation, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to no Terms of Communion, fearful in things indifferent, and bold in things unlawful; a Conſcience tender at one time, and fear'd at another, eaſie of belief in Surmiſes againſt Authority, but difficult and beyond all Precedent ſcrupulous in Poofs, that are for it; a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Revenge, and Ambition in the Great, of Mutiny and Sedition in the Meaner; a Spirit of Schiſme in matters Eccleſiaſtick, and of Faction in Temporals: if to all theſe the Lord ſhall have ſaid; as to that, <hi>you ſhall perſwade and Prevail, go forth and do ſo;</hi> They will then effect their Errand. By our Hatred of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, by our Frowardneſs, and diſobedience, they ſeem to be now at Work: by theſe they will engage us into a Civil War, and expoſe us to a forain; and then will Arbitrary Government and Popery, things of forain growth, and Strangers to our Land, come in with Armed force, through the wide Breaches we have made our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But may God be more merciful yet to us, that ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99674:19"/>little deſerve it: check theſe unruly Spirits, that are gone out in the mid'ſt of us; and give us of his Holy Spirit. May He, that commands the Wind and the Sea, and they obey him; He that is not in tempeſts, nor earthquakes, but in the ſtill voyce; reſtrain the ſtriving, lay the ſwelling of the Waves, compoſe our minds, and aſſwage our animoſities; turn the hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Fathers, leſt he come and ſmite the Earth with a curſe. May he that has graciouſly joyn'd us in ſo many common advantages Spiritual, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, ſhed his love abroad in our hearts by his Holy Spirit; that as we have one Baptiſm, one Spirit, one Faith, one hope of our calling, ſo we may be before Him as one holy congregation: that as we have one Prince, one Law, one Intereſt, ſo we may be as a City at Unity in it ſelf. God unite us before himſelf, in his worſhip; and before the face of our enemies, for our Defence: that we may be an Example to thoſe of our Religion, that yet enjoy it undiſturb'd; and a Refuge, to thoſe that are Diſtreſſed: that we be not the Scandal now; and a little after, the Ruin of the Proteſtant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>To this effect let us beſeech Him that by his ſpirit he would give our Governours an affectionate zeal for his honour, for the good of his People; Long-ſuffering and Gentleneſs towards thoſe, who much need it: that He would poſſeſs the People with a reverent Love for the Majeſty of God, for his Vicegerent, with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Faithfulneſs, and Goodneſs: that he would endue all ſubordinate Magiſtrates with proper graces, with the ſteady reſolution of a true Fidelity to God, their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99674:20"/>Prince, and the Law: that he would grant, that we abuſe not wantonly the bleſſed means of our reformed Religion to Schiſm, or Hereſie; the Publick Quiet to Civil Diſcord, our Liberty to Faction, nor our Plenty to Luxury and Intemperance: That the Peace of God maybe on all our Conſciences, and the Joy of the Holy Ghoſt on our Minds: that our Fruit may be unto Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and our end Everlaſting Life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
